<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
                  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <!-- NOTE: TO GET A TEXT VERSION FROM THIS, TYPE "xmlto txt HOWTO.xml"  -->
  <title>HIPL User Manual</title>
  <chapter>
    <title>Warning</title>
    <para>
      HIPL code is currently at a very experimental level. Use at your own
      responsibility! Using VMWare or User Mode Linux is recommended for
      testing HIPL.
      </para>
    </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Requirements</title>
    <para>
      As the first requirement, you also need know the basics on Linux kernel
      compilation and usage. Refer to linux/README for further instructions.
    </para>
    <para>
      You need the following software to build and run the HIPL 
      software bundle:
    </para>
    <para>
      * Mandatory
    </para>
    <para>
     &nbsp; * Linux Operating System
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;* A BEET patched Linux 2.6 kernel with dummy device, XFRM,
      XFRM_USER, IPv6, IPsec and AES+3DES+SHA1 support
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;* OpenSSL-library and developer headers
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;* GNU make
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;* the latest versions of autoconf, automake, autoreconf and libtool
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;* perl, lorder
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;* iproute and its development headers
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;* iptables development headers
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;* glib (www.gtk.org) and development headers
    </para>
    <para>
      * Optional
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;* iputils-ping (or netkit-ping): ping, ping6
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;* ipsec-tools: setkey
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;* iptables userspace tools and IPv6 netfilter in the kernel
              (for the HIP firewall only)
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;* netcat6
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;* latex, dvips, dvipdf, fig2dev, docbook-utils (for building the
      HIPL documentation)
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;* java compiler for "jip" (java hip resolver) if you want to build
      HIP enabled java programs
    </para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title> Building the HIPL Documentation</title>
    <para>
      Architectural documentation:
    </para>
    <para>
     &nbsp; % cd hipl/doc
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;% make design_choices.dvi design_choices.ps design_choices.pdf
    </para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Compiling the Kernel</title>
    
    <para>
      If you haven't configured linux kernel before, please consult
      hipl/linux/README before doing that. We have some example
      configurations files in hipl/test/configs for "typical" systems. You
      can use one of those as a template, and modify it to suite the needs
      of your system. Read hipl/test/configs/README before doing so.
    </para>
    <para>
      The 2.6 kernel series should be compilable with both gcc 2.9x and 3.x
      series. We recommend the latter.
    </para>
    <para>
      HIPL kernel is in hipl/linux folder. Compile the kernel with
      at least the following options:
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;Legend: [*] built-in  [ ] excluded  &lt;M &gt; module  &lt; &gt; module capable
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;Code maturity level options
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;[*] Prompt for development and/or incomplete code/drivers
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;Processor type and features
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;Device Drivers ---&gt; Networking support ---&gt; Networking options
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;[*] TCP/IP networking
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;&lt;*&gt; The IPv6 protocol (EXPERIMENTAL)
    </para>
    <para>
      IPsec, IPv6 security support, SHA1 and 3DES should be auto enabled as
      dependencies after you have selected HIP. We recommend that you
      compile HIP as a kernel module, and the IPv6 support as built-in.
    </para>
    <para>
      HIP debugging is not mandatory, but use of it is highly recommended in
      order to get more information when problems arise. HIP debugging
      information is logged using syslog's facility "kernel" and priority
      "debug". Remember to set up your /etc/syslog.conf correctly if you do
      not see the log messages (see syslog.conf manual page for more info).
    </para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Compiling Userspace Applications</title>
    <para>
      After you have successfully compiled and installed the HIP kernel and
      rebooted both of the hosts, you need to compile the userspace
      applications in order to use HIP. Start by moving to the top level directory
      of HIPL:
      </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;cd hipl
    </para>
    <para>
      If the file autogen.sh exists (to test type ls autogen.sh), run it:
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;./autogen.sh
    </para>
    <para>
      Next, build the hipd, libinet6, tools and test directory as follows:
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;./configure &amp;&amp; make
    </para>
    <para>
      It is not necessary to "make install" the applications. You can
      execute them straight from their source directories. Note that making
      from the top directory does not currently build e.g. java libraries or
      telnet. Follow the instructions presented later in this document to
      build them.
    </para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Testing a HIP connection between two hosts</title>
    <para>
      HIPL developers test HIP using two machines called crash (3ffe::1) and
      oops (3ffe::2). They are used through this whole document as examples
      even though you probably have your own naming and addressing
      conventions.
      </para>
    <para>
      We expect that you have two hosts for testing HIP which will be
      referred to as "crash" and "oops". You should run these commands in
      the testing hosts as root. conntest-client-gai and
      conntest-server can also be run as a non-root user, with
      conntest-server using port numbers less than 1024 still requires root
      privileges.
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;ifconfig eth0 inet6 add 3ffe::1/64
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;cd somewhere/hipl
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;hipd/hipd # (to start as a background daemon process, add -b flag)
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;test/conntest-server tcp 1111
    </para>
    <para>
      Crash will act as the connection initiator, so we need to configure
      the hosts files of crash:
    </para>
    <para>
      crash:
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;/etc/hosts:
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;&nbsp;3ffe::1 oops
      </para>
    <para>
     &nbsp; /etc/hip/hosts:
      </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;&nbsp;HIT_OF_OOPS oops
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;ifconfig eth0 inet6 add 3ffe::2/64
      </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;cd somewhere/hipl
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;hipd/hipd
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;test/conntest-client-gai oops tcp 1111
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;&lt;type some text in crash, press enter and ctrl+d and you
      &nbsp;should see some text appearing in the output of the hosts&gt;
    </para>
    <para>
      This will setup a HIP connection between the two hosts (it may take a
      while if you are using virtual machines). You should replace
      HIT_OF_XXX with the HIT of the host XXX. The hip daemon loads (and
      creates if necessary) the host identities from /etc/hip automatically.
      If you want to know the HITs of the localhost, run "ifconfig dummy0" or
      "ip addr show dummy0".
    </para>
    <para>
      Mappings between HITs and IPv6 addresses are usually set up
      automatically with the hosts files. Manual configuration is also
      possible but not necessary:
    </para>
    <para>
	&nbsp;tools/hipconf add map PEER_HIT PEER_IP
    </para>
    <para>
      Link local IPv6 addresses are not supported well, so do not use
      them. Use global IPv6 addresses instead for testing. The reason for
      this is that it is hard to know if the peer belongs to the same local
      network as we are or not.
      </para>
    <para>
      See the log messages for information about the result of HIP base
      exchange and USAGI IPSec negotiation. Tcpdump or ethereal are good
      tools for dumping the network traffic during the base exchange.
    </para>
    <para>
      There is also a script called "hipsetup" in "hipl/test" directory for
      quick testing of the base exchange. Run it without arguments to see
      how it is used. The script requires some external applications that
      will be prompted if they are not found.
    </para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Closing HIP Security Associations Manually</title>
     <para>
      You can use the hipconf tool to reset HIP SAs manually. Type
      "hipconf rst all" to close all SAs. 
     </para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Testing Handover</title>
    <para>
      The handover code is based on draft-nikander-hip-mm-00
      specification. Not all of the features all yet implemented and the
      code quality is still far from bullet proof.
    </para>
    <para>
      A naive handover test example is below. It assumes that you have
      already established the base exchange between the hosts. You also need
      to have the nc6 tool which can be found from e.g. "www.freshmeat.net".
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;&lt;first, establish a HIP connection as intructed in the previous
      section&gt;
      </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;oops  # nc6 -l -p 12345
      </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;crash # nc6 &lt;the HIT of oops&gt; 12345
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;crash # &lt;type some text and press enter&gt;
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;oops  # &lt;the text that you typed in crash should appear in oops
      console&gt;
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;crash # ifconfig eth0 inet6 del 3ffe::1/64
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;crash # ifconfig eth0 inet6 add 3ffe::3/64
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;crash # &lt;type some text and press enter&gt;
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;oops  # &lt;the text that you typed in crash should appear in oops console&gt;
    </para>
    <para>
      Do not use link local addresses for the mobility scenarios for the
      hosts, unless you know what you are doing! For example, you are asking
      for trouble if you establish HIP SA between the mobile and
      correspondent node using link local addresses, and move the mobile
      node to a different network. The readdressing fails, because either
      node has no way of reaching the other node.
    </para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title> Compiling Java Applications</title>
    <para>
      HIPL software bundle includes also a java wrapper library to the HIP
      enabled libinet6 resolver library. The library is called "jip" and it
      is located in "path-to-hipl/jip".
      </para>
    <para>
      You need to have either Blackdown or Sun java jdk 1.4.x or later to
      compile jip. The code does *not* work on java 1.3.  The installation
      assumes that you are using Blackdown 1.4 jdk, but if you are Sun jdk
      or other version of blackdown java, just set up the environment
      variable "JAVA_HOME" to point to the correct java installation
      directory.
    </para>
    <para>
      Compile libinet6.so and jip:
    </para>
    <para>
      # cd path-to-hipl/libinet6
    </para>
    <para>
      # make libinet6.so
    </para>
    <para>
      # cd ../jip
    </para>
    <para>
      # make
    </para>
    <para>
      The outcome of the previous operation is jip/jip.jar which you should
      use in your java applications to enable HIP. You can also run "make
      apidoc" to build the Javadoc documentation into the directory
      path-to-hipl/doc/jip-api.
    </para>
    <para>
      There are three example java applications in "test" directory that you
      must compile manually with the following procedure:
      </para>
    <para>
      # cd ../test
    </para>
    <para>
      # javac -classpath ../jip/jip.jar HipClient.java
    </para>
    <para>
      # javac -classpath ../jip/jip.jar HipUserkeyClient.java
    </para>
    <para>
      # javac -classpath ../jip/jip.jar HipServer.java
    </para>
    <para>
      You should have setup your networking environment as explained in
      section "Testing a HIP Connection Between Two Hosts", that is, you
      should have configured your /etc/hosts and /etc/hip/hosts
      properly. However, hipd will automatically create your public keys,
      so you don't have to worry about them.
    </para>
    <para>
      You cannot quite convert your normal Java networking application to a
      HIP application by just setting the socket factories.  You will need
      to either ensure that a used host name always resolves only to IPv6
      addresses, or that you never pass host names to methods in Socket and
      ServerSocket classes.  This latter can be achieved by using the
      resolver methods in the HipAddress class as is done in the example.
    </para>
    <para>
      Run the example applications as follows:
    </para>
    <para>
      crash # cd path-to-hipl/test
    </para>
    <para>
      crash # ./java HipServer 12345
    </para>
    <para>
      oops # cd test
    </para>
    <para>
      oops # ./java HipClient crash 12345 54321
    </para>
    <para>
      &lt;wait for the prompt, type some text and press enter&gt;
    </para>
    <para>
      The shell script "test/java" contains some LD_PRELOAD, library and
      class path information necessary for executing the HIP enabled java
      applications.
    </para>
    <para>
      The HipUserkeyClient class is otherwise the same as the HipClient
      class, except that its optional fourth argument is the name of a file
      from which to read an application-specified endpoint.
    </para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>HIP Enabled Telnet</title>
    <para>
      We have modified netkit-telnet from usagi (www.linux-ipv6.org) to
      support native HIP API. HIP is a compile time option, so that you can
      see the required modifications to the code (ifdef USE_HIP). Here's how
      you compile the telnet applications:
    </para>
    <para>
	# cd test/telnetd
    </para>
    <para>
	# ./configure
    </para>
    <para>
	# make
    </para>
    <para>
      # cd ../telnet
    </para>
    <para>
	# ./configure
    </para>
    <para>
	# make
    </para>
    <para>
	
	oops  # telnetd/telnetd -debug 12345
      </para>
    <para>
	crash # telnet/telnet -l username oops 12345
    </para>
    <para>
	
      Note: the username must be non-root.
    </para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title> How to Use HIP in Other C Based Applications?</title>
    <para>
      Use one the following methods:
    </para>
    <para>
      1. Port it to use the native HIP API. See the telnet code for a
      practical example. The API is documented in url:
      http://hipl.hiit.fi/hipl/hip-native-api-final.pdf
    </para>
    <para>
      2. Relink the application to use the libinet6 library provided in the HIPL
      software bundle. Then, use either of the following methods:
    </para>
    <para>
      a) Set the AI_HIP flag in the getaddrinfo call. This will make the
      getaddrinfo function to return only HITs in the place of IP addresses
      (no IP addresses are returned). Also, the getaddrinfo function sends
      the HIT-to-IPv6-address mapping to the kernel.
      </para>
    <para>
      b) You are using the transparent mode in the resolver (see the
      HIP_TRANSPARENT_API compilation flag in libinet6/Makefile.in). Only
      relinking is required, no changes are needed in the application.
    </para>
    <para>
      3. Override the getaddrinfo function from the command line:
      http://www-106.ibm.com/developerworks/linux/library/l-glibc.html?ca=3Ddgr-ln=
    </para>
    <para>
      Note! Methods two and three assume two prequisites! First, the
      application must be IPv6 enabled because the implementation currently
      supports only IPv6. Second, the application must really use the
      getaddrinfo interface because otherwise the getaddrinfo hack
      (i.e. sending HIT-to-IPv6 mapping to the HIP module) does not work.
    </para>
    <para>
    4. Insert the HIT to /etc/hosts, instead of /etc/hip/hosts. Then, add
       the HIT-to-IP mapping with "hipconf add map HIT IP". This is the
       quick-and-dirty method...
    </para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
  <title>Testing HIP Rendezvous Server/Mechanism</title>
    <para>
      The rendezvous server is similar to the home agent in Mobile IP. The
      rendezvous server provides a stable IP for the responder and forwards
      the initial I1 packet to the current location of the responder.
      </para>
    <para>
      The rendezvous server is similar to the home agent in Mobile IP. The
      rendezvous server provides a stable IP for the responder and forwards
      the initial I1 packet to the current location of the responder.
    </para>
    <para>
      Prerequisites:
    </para>
    <para>
      Kernel must be compiled with the following extra option(s) included.
    </para>
    <para>
      [*]  HIP: Rendezvous Mechanism 
    </para>
    <para>
      The hipconf tool must support rvs option:
    </para>
    <para>
      hipconf rvs &lt;hit&gt; &lt;ip&gt;
    </para>
    <para>
      For now it is best if all the hosts involved in communications have
      the Rendezvous Mechanism option enabled. Although, for the initiator
      this should not be a requirement. Also, you should have run the base
      exchange once without rendezvous server to get familiar how the
      /etc/hosts and /etc/hip/hosts are configured.
    </para>
    <para>
      The participants:
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;I = Initiator
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;RVS = The Rendezvous server
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;R = Responder
    </para>
    <para>
      The idea is that I wants to connect to R's HIT but only knows RVS's IP
      address (and that RVS is representing R). We'll show how to use RVS
      the native HIP example applications (although you can do it with
      nc6 or the other conntest test applications).
    </para>
    <para>
      Steps:
    </para>
    <para>
      -----
    </para>
    <para>
      	  1. Start and initialize HIP module in each host:
    </para>
    <para>
      2. At the initiator, you must modify the "/etc/hosts" file. In the file,
      responder's hostname must be mapped to the IPv6 address of the rendezvous
      server. It must not be mapped to the responder's IPv6 address, or
      otherwise the rendezvous server is not used at all!
    </para>
    <para>
      The "/etc/hip/hosts" file should contain the hostname and HIT of the
      responder as in the normal base exchange execution.
    </para>
    <para>
      3. R has to tell the RVS that it would like to use RVS's services:
    </para>
    <para>
      responder # hipconf rvs &lt;RVS-hit&gt; &lt;RVS-ip&gt;
    </para>
    <para>
      This will establish a HIP SA between the rendezvous server and the responder.
    </para>
    <para>
      4. Put some server listening at R:
    </para>
    <para>
      responder # test/conntest-server-native tcp 5000
    </para>
    <para>
      5. Start a connection at I:
    </para>
    <para>
      initiator # test/conntest-client-native &lt;responder-hostname&gt; tcp 5000
    </para>
    <para>
      6. Type some text...
    </para>
    <para>
      Notes:
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;* The implemented mechanism is simple forwarding of I1 packet with 
      source and  destination IPv6 addresses rewritten.
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;* No changes were  made to the REA / mm-code,  which means that, for 
      example, the double jump scenario does not work.
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;* Changes will be made when upgrade from mm-00 to mm-02 is finished.
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;* The mechanism  does not comply 100% with the RVS draft.
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;* We don't use REA TLV in R1 (from responder to initiator). The same 
      functionality is achieved by using the sender's IP address of 
      the R1 packet.
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;* The VIA_RVS TLV is also left out, since it is meant only for 
      diagnostic purposes, and doesn't really add anything to the
      implementation, except for bugs. :)
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;* The rendezvous mechanism is not yet guaranteed to be interoperable 
		with other implementations than HIPL
    </para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title> Using HIP BOS support</title>
    <para>
      &nbsp;* To generate a BOS packet (sent to the global multicast address
      on all interfaces), use the following command:
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;&nbsp;hipconf BOS
    </para>
    <para>
      &nbsp;BOS-aware hosts will record the machine's HOST ID, HIT, and IP address.
    </para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    
    <title>Accessing the kernel peer list</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>You can access the kernel's list of known HIP peers using the native
	  getendpointinfo name resolution interface.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>By default, the interface first checks the /etc/hip/hosts file for
	  a matching host. If one is not found, the kernel is queried for its
	  list of known HIP peers and the list is examined for matches.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>To only check the kernel list, set the hints.ei_flags to 
	  AI_HIP | AI_KERNEL_LIST. This will use only the kernel list and will
	  not check the hosts file.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>To retrieve the list of known peers from the kernel, set the 
	  hints.ei_flags to AI_HIP | AI_KERNEL_LIST and the nodename to NULL.
	  This will query the kernel for the list and return the entire
	  list.</para>
	</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>HIP Firewall</title>

        <para>Ip6tables must define that HIP and ESP packets are
              queued in the user-space.  These rules must be inserted
              so that they precede any other firewall rules that might
              concern the HIP and ESP packets. If ESP packet filtering
              is not necessary the ip6tables rules concerning ESP
              packets (-p 50) can be left out.</para>

        <para>ip6tables -A FORWARD -p 99 -j QUEUE</para>
        <para>ip6tables -A FORWARD -p 50 -j QUEUE</para>
        <para>ip6tables -A INPUT -p 99 -j QUEUE</para>
        <para>ip6tables -A INPUT -p 50 -j QUEUE</para>
        <para>ip6tables -A OUTPUT -p 99 -j QUEUE</para>
        <para>ip6tables -A OUTPUT -p 50 -j QUEUE</para>

        <para>ip6_queue must be loaded with: "modprobe ip6_queue"</para>

        <para>Firewall can be started with "./firewall &lt;file_name&gt;"
              "timeout value" at firewall directory, where file_name
              is path of the file containing the firewall rules and
              timeout value is the connection timeout value in
              seconds.  If connection timeout is defined as zero or
              negative, the connection timeout checking is not
              used. Rules in the file must be separated with
              newline. The firewall (currently) prints out debug
              information from rule parsing test functions and from
              filtering packets.</para>

        <para>Rules follow (loosely) the syntax of Linux Iptables with
        following syntax:</para>

        <para>Basic format of rule:</para>

        <para>HOOK [match] TARGET</para>

        <para>Here HOOK is one of the netfilter hooks: "INPUT",
              "OUTPUT", "FORWARD".  Target is either "ACCEPT" or
              "DROP", whether packet should be allowed or not.  Match
              is a combination of filtering option described below.</para>

        <para>Filtering options:</para>

        <para>-src_hit [!] &lt;hit value&gt; --src_hi &lt;file name&gt;</para>

        <para>Matches source HIT of packet. HI can be given with
              --src_hi option and by defining path to a public key
              file as an argument. This causes sender signatures to be
              verified. The file name must contain either "_rsa_" or
              "_dsa_" to define whether RSA or DSA is used as
              algorithm.</para>
 
        <para>-dst_hit [!] &lt;hit&gt;</para>

        <para>Matches destination HIT of packet.</para>

        <para>-type [!] &lt;hip packet type&gt;</para>

        <para>Matches HIP packet type. Type is one of following: 
              "I1", "R1", "I2", "R2", "CER", "UPDATE", "NOTIFY", "CLOSE",
              "CLOSE_ACK"</para>

        <para>-i [!] &lt;incoming interface&gt;</para>

        <para>Matches incoming interface. Argument contains name of
              the interface. Can not be used for rules in OUTPUT hook
              as packet has no incoming interface in that case.</para>

        <para>-o [!] &lt;outgoing interface&gt;</para>

        <para>Matches outgoing interface. Argument contains name of
              the interface. Can not be used for rules in INPUT hook
              as packet has no outgoing interface in that case.</para>

        <para>-state [!] &lt;state&gt; --verify_responder --accept_mobile</para>

        <para>Matches state of HIP association: "NEW" or
              "ESTABLISHED". ESP packets are also filtered as part of
              the connection. With "--verify_responder" option the
              firewall stores responder HI from R1 packet and uses it
              for verifying signatures in the packets. With
              --accept_mobile option, the firewall may establish state
              for existing connection when a mobile host enters the
              network protected by the firewall. In practice this
              requires bringing down the previous interface and
              bringing up a new one in the new network.</para>


        <para>Management interface:</para>

        <para>Firewall management interface contains functions for
              altering rules of running firewall. Functions are
              defined in firewall/rule_management.h and implemented in
              firewall/rule_management.c. Rule_management.c also
              contains functions for copying, comparing and freeing
              rules, etc. If any functions are needed outside the
              rule_management they can be defined in the header file.</para>

        <para>The argument "hook" in the rule is the Netfilter hook
              for which rule is intended. The hooks are defined in
              linux/netfilter_ipv6.h as NF_IP6_LOCAL_IN,
              NF_IP6_FORWARD, NF_IP6_LOCAL_OUT.</para>

        <para>The argument rule is structure describing the rule
              defined in rule_management.h. The structure contains
              pointers to options. The pointer value must be NULL,
              when option is not defined. The structures for options
              are also defined in rule_management.h. Function: rule *
              parse_rule(char * string) can be used for creating a
              rule structure from a string. This also inspects that
              the rule syntax is correct.</para>

        <para>void insert_rule(const struct rule * rule, int hook):</para>

        <para>Inserts argument rule into with the hook. Insert makes
              local copy of the argument rule.</para>

        <para>int delete_rule(const struct rule * rule, int hook):</para>

        <para>Deletes the local rule that is equal to the argument
              rule. </para>

        <para>GList * list_rules(int hook):</para>

        <para>creates a copy of the rule list and returns it. Caller
               must take care of freeing the returned list.</para>

        <para>int flush(int hook):</para>

        <para>Clears all rules.</para>
  </chapter>

</book>    

